## Bruno de Paula Kinoshita

Brazilian, married, 32 years old. Auckland CBD – Auckland – New Zealand. M: +64 (021) 104 2131, kinow@apache.org, GitHub: kinow

### **Personal Profile**

I am an honest, and focused employee that is always trying to deliver software with good quality. I have worked in many different projects in the past ten years, in areas such as telecommunications, banks, credit bureau, retail and insurance. And had different roles as well, such as programmer, quality engineer, devops, architect and big data engineer.

I am a very calm and easy-going person. I enjoy challenging work environment, learning and applying new technologies, participating in Open Source projects and meeting new people.

I am fluent in English, Portuguese, with good understanding of Spanish, and basic understanding of Japanese.

## **Key Skills and Qualities**

- Writing software that is easy to maintain, with documentation, tests and best practices
- Scaling tools with messaging, publish-subscribe systems and scale-out solutions
- Software automation with shell, Perl, Python, Jenkins, Make, Oozie, and other build tools
- Systems integration, understanding how these systems communicate with each other, prevent chaotic situations and writing plug-ins, adapters and glue code
- Systems builds, with source code management branching strategies, automated testing, continuous integration and continuous delivery
- Monitoring for systems and company processes (KPI's)
- Proposing architectures or solutions that adapt to the company reality, fixing existing problems and maximizing agility
- Working with large datasets and distributed systems
- Java (Maven, Struts, Spring), Perl, Shell, Python, R, JavaScript (jQuery, Backbone.js, Node.js), Hadoop (MapReduce, Hive, Pig), Linux, SSO, PHP (Codelgniter, Laravel), Databases (Oracle, MySQL, Hibernate, Jooq, ActiveRecord), semantics and linked data, bioinformatics and code quality and design patterns.
- WFS, WMS, SOS
- Linux (Slackware, Ubuntu, Debian, RHEL, SLES), Shell scripting, gdb, strace, netstat
- Puppet, Ansible, SaltStack, AWS

### **Achievements**

- Awarded PMS status in Apache Commons in October 2016.

- Awarded PMC status in Apache Jena in March 2015.
- Awarded committer status in Apache Jena in January 2015.
- Awarded committer status in Apache Commons, becoming a member of the Apache Software Foundation in August 2012.
- Organized the Jenkins Meetup in Sao Paulo, in 2012 and 2013, talking with partners and sponsors, and bringing the tool creator, Kohsuke Kawaguchi, to Brazil both times. This helped to establish a local community and network of professionals.

## **Work Experience**

## September 2016 – Present Spark Ventures

#### Full Stack Software Engineer

- Part of the ventures Platform team, responsible for business cases and solutions for all other ventures
- Integration between Spring Boot and AWS Key Management Service (KMS)
- Configure New Relic monitoring, covering key parts of systems, and also integrating with internal systems for alerting and dashboards
- Security review in Java Spring Boot applications

## April 2015 – September 2016

## NIWA - National Institute of Water and Atmospheric Research

#### Software Developer/System Operations

- Responsible for the Continuous Integration and development pipeline in Jenkins.
- Automation and build scripts with Ant, Grunt.JS, Maven, Python, Perl, Groovy, and Shell Script.
- Responsible to maintain and extend the middleware stack: GeoServer, GeoNetworks, Sissvoc, 52North SOS, KISTERS KiWIS SOS.
- Work with researchers to write Python tools to capture and display data from sensors and devices with serial ports and WebSockets.
- Review infrastructure for security issues, misconfiguration in firewall and reverse proxy, and fix potential security issues.
- Liaise with IT Operations, System Development team, researchers and other internal departments in several different projects to deliver software. Also work with other organizations like NeSI and national weather services on third party tools.

## June 2014 – March 2015 Boa Vista Serviços (part of Equifax Brazil)

#### Senior Big Data Engineer

– Deploy a Big Data cluster with Hadoop, Hive, Pig, Impala, Hue, Flume.

- Create ontologies based on other existing ontologies and adapted to internal systems.
- Write web applications in Java (Jersey, Jooq) and PHP (SPARQL, Laravel, Semantic-UI, JQuery) to interface with data generated in the cluster.
- Automate crawlers and data movement and ingestion processes.
- Participate in internal committees for designing and adapting new processes according to the company existing governance model.
- Meetings with service and tool providers to select new partners.
- Create a data matching/linking process that runs in Java and in the Hadoop cluster, using deterministic and probabilistic techniques and algorithms.
- Create a monitoring panel for systems and KPI's.
- Write documentation and business cases.
- Integrate Talend Open Studio, Tableau, IBM Netezza and other solutions with the Hadoop cluster.
- Provide training and internal workshops.

# January 2013 – May 2014 <u>Tokio Marine Seguradora (Tokio Marine Holdings, Inc.)</u>

#### Senior System Architect

- Create an ActiveMQ cluster to be used by several departments.
- Choose new tools and work flows for process and business needs.
- Participate in company workshops for promoting best practices and corporate services (what reduced the amount of code being written and maintained by multiple departments)
- Write a REST web service for internal departments to send SMS's.
- Write a REST web service for internal departments to digitally sign PDF's.
- Create a Single Sign-On corporate system, using OpenAM and Kerberos.
- Contribute to the company Liferay portal project, providing the infrastructure, SSO and modules deployment.
- Create a corporate KPI and processes monitoring panel, using Graphite, Dashing and glue code, which resulted in a new corporate culture and better level of quality in internal and external services.

# January 2012 – December 2013 <u>Tokio Marine Seguradora (Tokio Marine Holdings, Inc.)</u>

### Senior Infrastructure Engineer

- Automate infrastructure using Jenkins, Shell, Puppet.
- Create a new environment with JBoss clusters.
- Create Linux services for several applications that were being started manually.
- Create monitoring services to replace existing legacy systems that were consuming too much CPU and memory to monitor the applications.
- Automate systems deployments, to avoid manual intervention.

#### October 2011 – December 2012

#### Tokio Marine Seguradora (Tokio Marine Holdings, Inc.)

#### Senior Software Engineer

- Maintain legacy applications and slowly introduce code enhancements in JEE applications written with Java and JavaScript, deployed to an OC4J.
- Mavenize the code and write initial tests.
- Create daily builds with Jenkins.
- Create Subversion hooks for e-mails, metrics and trigger jobs in Jenkins.

## July 2011 – September 2011 Lojas Riachuelo

#### Senior System Analyst

- Refactor an existing POS application.
- Propose a new architecture for the POS, that enabled rapid application development and testing.
- Split a large legacy application into Maven modules.
- Write automated test suite.
- Create wrappers for Delphi and C/C++ back end and devices (printer, drawer, biometry) code.

## January 2010 – June 2011 Vivo (Portugal Telecom/Telefónica)

#### Senior Software Quality Engineer

- Gather metrics from the enterprise CRM and its modules to prevent bugs, enhance quality and help QA team.
- Set up of a QA environment integrating Subversion, Jenkins, E-mail relays, Sonar, TestLink and the company's reporting system.
- Write a plug-in (later open sourced) to integrate Jenkins and TestLink to run automated tests and avoid wasting testers hours when the suite was broken.
- Profiling and tuning of the CRM with YourKit and Eclipse Memory Analyzer.
- Patches and reports on metrics and issues reported by Sonar.
- Training for test and development departments on Jenkins, Sonar, and code quality.
- Creation of a performance suite with SOAP-UI and JMeter to provide benchmarks for Vivo solutions.
- Write several tools to help testers and developers to use an Oracle ESB.
- Participate in RFP's from other companies and provide technical feedback.

## April 2008 – December 2009 Nossa Caixa Bank (now part of Bank of Brazil)

#### Senior Software Engineer

- Java support for development teams.
- Participate in a committee to choose the company best practices and coding standards.
- Promote Java within .NET and mainframe departments, as the company was adapting its systems to a new platform.
- Maintain and write new modules for systems integration between .NET and Java, and the company's mainframes, using MQSeries, DirectConnect, Uniface and Java within Z/OS and Z-Linux.
- Debug COBOL programs with Roscoe to identify integration problems.
- Provide Java training for departments in different sites.
- Participate in meetings with providers and partners to assess how well new tools and technologies would fit in the company's systems architecture.

#### June 2007 – March 2008 Claro (América Móvil)

#### Junior System Analyst

- Write MMS/MM7 module for the middle ware platform, in Java EE using JMS, EJB, JNDI/LDAP and JCA. This module attended over a million users in Brazil per month.
- Map the billing process with the VAS process for inconsistencies and process improvements.
- Write a Struts web application to manage SMS broadcast marketing campaigns.
   This system had to maximize broadcast windows, control throttle and throughput when integrating with engineer, billing and marketing systems.
- Replace the company Captcha used for sending SMS's as it was being used by attackers to mass-send spam.

### January 2006 – May 2007 Claro (América Móvil)

#### Junior System Technician

- Write parts of a JEE client application with Java Swing, managing threads, opening Sockets and using system resources. This application depended heavily of JNDI/LDAP for configuration of the middle ware application.
- Maintain a monitoring panel and applets used by managers for KPI's.

## July 2004 – December 2005 Claro (América Móvil)

#### Value Added Services Trainee

- Three months in the On-going Systems department to understand service desk, incidents and learn about the company departments and systems.
- Talk directly to partners of the company and set up their accounts in the middle ware platform for SMS marketing campaigns.

- Monitor platform logs.
- Produce management reports.

## **Education and Training**

2003/2007	<b>Bachelor of Science in Information Systems</b> . Dissertation on Decision Systems with Fuzzy Logic. Mackenzie Presbyterian University, Sao Paulo, Sao Paulo. Brazil.
2003	<b>Microsoft Certified Solutions Associate</b> career, and MCP certification. Brás & Figueiredo. Sao Paulo, Sao Paulo.
2004	Genexus Programming. Procwork. Sao Paulo, Sao Paulo – Brazil.
2006	COBIT & Sarbanes-Oxley. Claro S/A. Sao Paulo, Sao Paulo – Brazil.
2007	Web Components Developer with Servlets & JSP Technology (SL-314). Sun Microsystems. Sao Paulo, Sao Paulo – Brazil.  Biometry applied in computer networks security. (with Dr. Maria Inês Lopes Brosso). Mackenzie Presbyterian University. Sao Paulo, Sao Paulo – Brazil.  Information Security. Claro S/A. Sao Paulo, Sao Paulo – Brazil.
2008	Business Intelligence. Claro S/A. Sao Paulo, Sao Paulo – Brazil.  Hands-On Websphere Application Server 6.1 (with Cristiane M. Ferreira).  IBM. Sao Paulo, Sao Paulo – Brazil.  CA Harvest Software Change Admin & Config. CA. Sao Paulo, Sao Paulo – Brazil.  Basic concepts of change management. Nossa Caixa Bank (Sao Paulo state bank). Sao Paulo, Sao Paulo – Brazil.
2008/2009	<b>Post graduation diploma in Business Administration</b> . Case study of a Rotary International Rotaract club using Balanced Scorecards to manage its projects. Presbyterian University Mackenzie, Sao Paulo, Sao Paulo. Brazil.
2012	Infrastructure Management with Puppet. Instruct Treinamento. Sao Paulo, Sao Paulo – Brazil.
2015	Introduction to Big Data with Apache Spark. Edx. Introduction to Linux. Edx. Explore Statistics with R. Edx. NZ NVIDIA Workshop Auckland. NeSI and NVIDIA. Auckland, New Zealand. Web Of Science training. Thomson Reuters. Auckland, New Zealand. NCBI Now! An online workshop that introduces NGS with a hands-on

component in the cloud! ORAU Learning. Statistics and R for the Life Sciences. Edx.

**Linux Foundation Certified Systems Engineer**. Linux Academy.

2016 **OWASP Training (part of OWASP New Zealand Day 2016)**. Auckland University. Auckland, New Zealand.

**Introduction to C++**. Edx.

Telling Your Story With Esri Story Maps. Esri.

Achieving Interoperability Using ArcGIS and OGC Standards. Esri.

Basics of Geographic Coordinate Systems. Esri.

**Microbiology and Forensic Science (MicFor)**. Jordan University of Science and Technologya, via Open2Study.

Come Rain or Shine: Understanding the Weather. University of Reading, via FutureLearn.

**CS107: C++ Programming**. Saylor Academy.

**Explore Animation**. NFTS – National Film and Television School, via FutureLean.

**Transcriptomics** – Winter Bootcamp 2016. Auckland University, Bioinformatics Institute and NZGL. Auckland, New Zealand.

**Metabarcoding** – Winter Bootcamp 2016. Auckland University, Bioinformatics Institute and NZGL. Auckland, New Zealand.

Apache Spark Essentials. Linux Academy.

AWS Concepts. Linux Academy.

## **Certifications**

- 2003 MCP (Microsoft Certified Professional) Windows 2000.
- 2006 SCJP (Sun Certified Java Programmer).
- 2008 **CA** Software Change Manager Administration.
- 2009 SCWCD (Sun Certified Web Component Developer).
- 2009 ITIL Foundation V2.
- 2009 **COBIT** Foundation V4.1.
- 2010 Certificate of completion for Parasoft Agile Development Quality practices and Techniques Training.
- 2010 **ISTQB** Certified Tester CTFL.
- 2011 Professional Scrum Master I (scrum.org).
- 2011 **IELTS** General Training, score: 7.5.
- 2015 **LFCE** Linux Foundation Certified Engineer.

## **Interests and Hobbies**

- Slack line, swimming and Judo
- Spend time with family and friends
- Meeting new people and learning about new cultures
- Irish Music and History
- Science fiction books and movies
- Bioinformatics, semantic web, GIS and linked data

### **Publications**

- Advanced Jenkins Management. Revista MundoJ, May/Jun, No 59 http://www.-mundoj.com.br. May, 2013.
- Apache Functor Programação Funcional em Java. Revista MundoJ, Mar/Apr, No
   52 http://www.mundoj.com.br. March, 2012.
- Desenvolvimento ágil em Java com Jenkins e Sonar. Devcast Magazine No 2. http://www.devmedia.com.br/revista-devcast-magazine-2. February 2012.
- On integrating Continuous Integration and Test Management. TQA News Software Test Pro. http://www.softwaretestpro.com. December, 2011.
- Faça seus Testes Falarem TAP Aprenda como funciona e a utilizar o protocolo de testes TAP com Java (in conjunction with Anderson dos Santos and César Fernandes de Almeida). Revista MundoJ, Mar/Apr, No 46 – http://www.mundoj.com.br. May, 2011.
- Manage your Automated Tests with TestLink and Hudson Automated Software Testing Magazine No 1, Volume 3 - http://www.automatedtestinginstitute.com/. March, 2011.
- Test Automation with TestLink and Hudson (in conjunction with Anderson dos Santos) – Testing Experience No 12 – http://www.testingexperience.com. December, 2010.
- Measuring Software Quality with Metrics Why Static and Dynamic Analysis should walk hand-in-hand - Testing Experience No 11 – http://www.testingexperience.com. September, 2010.

## **Presentations and events**

- eResearch NZ 2016 "BioUno Building Pipelines for life sciences with Jenkins".
   Queenstown, New Zealand. February, 2015.
- Mozilla Science Global Sprint 2015 "BioUno". (Host site in Auckland at NIWA).
   Auckland, New Zealand. June, 2015.
- Jenkins Meetup Sao Paulo 2013 "Developing Jenkins plug-ins". (Local host and organizer of the event). Sao Paulo, Sao Paulo, Brazil. December, 2012.
- STPCon Speed Geeking Software Test Professionals Conference 2012. "Why TAP matters?". New Orleans, Louisiania, United States of America. March, 2012. http://www.stpcon.com
- STPCon Software Test Professionals Conference 2012. "Test Management in your Continuous Integration Process with Jenkins and TestLink". New Orleans, Louisiania, United States of America. March, 2012. http://www.stpcon.com
- JavaOne Latin America 2011. "Measuring the quality of your code during Continuous Integration". Sao Paulo, Sao Paulo, Brazil. November, 2011. http://www.oracle.com/javaone/lad-pt
- JCertif 2011. "Make your tests speak TAP". CCF. Brazzaville. Congo. Setembro, 2011. http://www.jcertif.com
- The Developers Conference 2011. "Botando o Jenkins para rodar seus testes". Universidade Estácio de Sá. Sao Jose, Santa Catarina, Brazil. July, 2011. http://www.thedevelopersconference.com.br
- Belgium Testing Days 2011. "How to Automate Tests Using TestLink and Hudson". Sheraton Brussels Airport Hotel. Brussels. Belgium. February, 2011. http://www.belgiumtestingdays.com

Encontro Ágil 2010. "Automatização com TestLink e Hudson". IME-USP (Statistics and Mathematics Institute – Sao Paulo University). Sao Paulo, Sao Paulo. Brazil. November, 2010. http://www.encontroagil.com.br

## **Open Source projects**

I have participated in the following Open Source projects, as creator or contributor.

JenkinsJenkins CCM plug-inTestLinktap4j

Jenkins TestLink plug-in
 Jenkins TAP plug-in
 Apache Commons Functor
 Apache Commons Lang

Jenkins R plug-in
 Jenkins Image Gallery plug-in
 Jenkins PBS plug-in
 Jenkins Uno-Choice plug-in
 Nestor-QA

– java-testlink-api – Mozilla Science

#### <u>Awards</u>

- "Proactive Communicator For excellent communications". NIWA Information Technology Awards. February/2016. Auckland, New Zealand.
- Voted for embodiment of the Spirit of GovHack for amazing team work. Gov-Hack. July / 2016. Auckland, New Zealand.

## Referees

Available upon request, from companies from Brazil and New Zealand.